Guide to the Bruno Foa Papers, 1927-2005 RL.00403
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Bruno Foa papers
1927-2005
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Foa, Bruno
RL.00403
3.5 Linear Feet
Italian-born economist, lawyer, consultant, and professor. Collection contains Foa’s published and unpublished writings; files and correspondence from positions he held including his term as a fellow at Princeton University (1940-1942), as Director of the Bureau of Latin American Research (1941-1943), on the Federal Reserve Board, as a consultant for other economics projects, and as professor and guest lecturer at several Universities; a memoir by Foa; his biography of the Foa family; and personal correspondence among his family members, travel documents, and memos about the destination during trips to Italy, Jerusalem, Spain, South America and Somalia.
2500 Items
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. The library may require up to 48 hours to retrieve these materials for research use.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Provenance
The Bruno Foa papers were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a gift in 2006.
Biographical Note
Bruno Foa (1905-1999) was an Italian-born, Jewish economist, lawyer, consultant, and professor. Educated in Italy as an economist and lawyer, Foa became Italy's youngest full professor of economics at age 28. In 1937, he married Lisa Haimann, a refugee from Munich, and they moved to London in 1938. While in London, Foa worked for the British Broadcasting Company, the National Institute of Economic and Social Research, and guest lectured at the London School of Economics.
In 1940, Foa moved his family to the United States. He began work at Princeton University on a Rockefeller Foundation Grant and later moved to Washington D.C. where he worked for the Rockefeller Foundation, the Office of Inter-American Affairs, the Bureau of Latin American Affairs and the Federal Reserve Board.
In 1945 he settled in New York City where he became an economic consultant focusing on Italian reconstruction and economic development after World War II. During this time he published his book on Italian monetary reconstruction and wrote many articles in both American and Italian journals about financial development. He taught at Yale University and the University of Pennsylvania among many other guest lecturer positions.
His work afforded him the opportunity to travel many times to Europe, especially Italy, and other destinations around the globe including Jerusalem, Somalia, and South America. In Europe and America, he encountered, knew, and worked with a variety of eminent men and women from a wide range of professions: economists, writers, architects, businessmen, politicians, labor leaders, and Zionists. His papers include his correspondence and works collected over 65 years.
Collection Overview
Collection contains Foa’s published and unpublished writings; files and correspondence from positions he held including his term as a fellow at Princeton University (1940-1942), as Director of the Bureau of Latin American Research (1941-1943), on the Federal Reserve Board, as a consultant for other economics projects, and as professor and guest lecturer at several Universities; a memoir by Foa; his biography of the Foa family; and personal correspondence among his family members, travel documents, and memos about the destination during trips to Italy, Jerusalem, Spain, South America and Somalia.
Economics; Economists -- Italy; Economics -- United States; Board of Governors of the Federal Reserve System (U.S.); Foa, Bruno; Foa, Bruno; Latin American Research Bureau
- Correspondence, 1927-1995, 8 folders
  Scope and Contents note
  Professional correspondence contains letters from persons and economists in Europe and America, notably Irving Fischer, Gustav Cassel, Wesley Mitchell, Achille Loria, Luigi Einaudi, Dennis Robertson, Lionel Robbins, Friedrich von Hayek, Piero Sraffa and others. Contents mostly concern writings and introductions when Foa moved from Italy to London and later to America. Personal correspondence is mostly with his wife and family.
  - Professional correspondence, with written note about letters by Foa, 1927-1995, 5 folders (Box 1)
  - Professional correspondence with Riccardo Faucci, 1990 (Box 1)
  - Personal correspondence, 1930-1960, 2 folders (Box 1)
- Professional materials, 1938-1956, 11 folders
  Professional materials consists of documents concerning Burno Foa's professional career as an economist. Documents are included from his time as a fellow at Princeton University (1940-1942), Director of the Bureau of Latin American Research (1941-1943), member of the Board of Governors of the Federal Reserve Board (1944-1945), as a guest lecturer at Yale and other universities, and as a consultant for the UN, the Italian Embassy in Washington, the Board of Economic Warfare and others.
  - Princeton university, 1939-1941 (Box 1)
  - Princeton, edited Italian manuscript, n.d. (Box 1)
  - Latin American affairs, correspondence, 1941-1943 (Box 1)
  - Latin American affairs, memos, 1941-1943 (Box 1)
  - Latin American affairs, confidential memos, 1941-1943 (Box 1)
  - Latin American affairs, confidential booklets, 1942-1943 (Box 1)
  - Guest lectures, 1938-1944 (Box 1)
  - Federal reserve board, reports and correspondence, 1944-1945 (Box 1)
  - Yale university, lectures and correspondence, 1949-1953 (Box 1)
  - Economic consulting, memos, speeches, and reports, 1948-1956 (Box 1)
  - Newspaper and magazine clippings, n.d. (Box 1)
  - Certificate from Italian president awarding Foa the honor of Ufficiale, 1958 (Oversize-folder 1)
- Travel, 1946-1960, 10 folders
  During his professional career, Foa traveled to Jerusalem, Mexico, Argentina, Brazil, Somalia and throughout Europe. Folders contain mostly personal correspondence and travel documents, but where otherwise noted also contain reports and observations of his destinations.
  - Italy and Israel,correspondence, 1946 (Box 1)
  - Italy and Israel, travel documents and writings, 1946 (Box 1)
  - Italy, correspondence, 1948 (Box 1)
  - Italy, correspondence and travel documents, 1952 (Box 2)
  - Spain and Italy, correspondence and hotel opening announcements, 1953 (Box 2)
  - Israel and Europe, 1954, 2 folders (Box 2)
  - South America, 1954-1958 (Box 2)
  - Mission to Somalia, reports, 1960 (Box 2)
  - Mission to Somalia, correspondence, 1960 (Box 2)
- Writings, 1949-1989, 12 folders
  Writings includes drafts, notes, and outlines of published and unpublished works written by Bruno Foa. In some instances, the files contain reviews and responses to his work from other economists.
  - Personal information, biography, resume, timeline of life, n.d. (Box 2)
  - Monetary Reconstruction in Italy, reviews, correspondence, 1949 (Box 2)
  - Harper's articles, submissions and drafts, 1949-1951 (Box 2)
  - Marshall Revisited in the Age of DNA, Journal of Post-Keynesian Economics, drafts, 1982 (Box 2)
  - Recollections of Augusto Graziani, notes and correspondence, 1984 (Box 2)
  - The Foa family biography, drafts and notes, 1985 (Box 2)
  - Memoir, Rite of Passage, notes and drafts in Italian, 1986 (Box 2)
  - Memoir, Rite of Passage, two edited drafts in Italian, 1984 (Box 2)
  - Memoir, Rite of Passage, drafts in English, 1989 (Box 2)
  - Italy and the Italians, outline and drafts, 1987 (Box 2)
  - Miscellaneous writings, English, n.d. (Box 2)
  - Miscellaneous writings, Italian, n.d. (Box 2)
- Printed Materials, 1930-2005, 8 folders
  Printed materials contains published works by Foa and others in both English and Italian. This series contains complete journals as well as stand alone articles.
  - The World in 1952: Some Predictions, American Psychological Association, collected by Hadley Cantril, 1943 (Box 2)
  - Harper's magazine, Foa's published article and letters to the editor, 1949 (Box 2)
  - Monetary Construction in Italy, published copy in English, 1949 (Box 2)
  - Miscellaneous loose articles, 1930-1960 (Box 2)
  - Published articles and journals written by Foa, English, 1939-1953 (Box 2)
  - Published articles and journals written by Foa, Italian, 1927-1990, 2 folders (Box 3)
  - Published articles and journals written by others, English and Italian, 1935-2005, 2 folders (Box 3)
- Photographs 1928-1968, 1 folder
  Photographs of Bruno and Lisa Foa and friends.
  - Photos, 1928-1968 (Box 3)